So as a final
example, another UML state diagram
to be translated into
a flat state diagram.
What do we have
in front of us now?
Here again we have no regions, so
it's a bit like example 1, still without
regions, but this time with
a history node (namely that one).
So like
here no regions,
but a hierarchical state and history
(in the specific case, flat history).
So what we don't have
as an example is a
combination where both
regions and history occur.
And in fact, we
won't have that interacting occur
in our flat-knock examples
that you're supposed to solve.
We have the simple case with no
regions and no history, the intermediate case
with regions and no history, and we
have the case with no regions but history.
These are our
examples 1, 2,
3, and you should be able
to do the same for analogous examples.
What will be the approach
to deal with the example?
First, again as
in the simple case,
that is, as in example 1 (that is,
what was here as an approach, as a strategy):
Keep the
simple states,
translate things that occur at the
edge of these hierarchical states appropriately,
keep the entries and exits, other transitions
(that do not somehow affect the edge,
but for example such transitions outside
or such transitions inside) simple, and keep
the outer start state also as
the start state (while the inner start
states can disappear and are at
most used to translate entries correctly).
This will also
be the basic strategy.
Of course, having this
history node changes something.
And what has
to change there?
Well, if we leave
such a hierarchical state that
has a history node in it, then we
know that if we're going to come back here
later, and in particular we're
going to do that via a
history entry, then we would need to know
where we were last in that hierarchical state.
So if we leave the state via e, we
still have to know later when we return whether
we left this hierarchical state from C
or from D. How can we remember that?
How can
we remember this?
Only in states of
the flat state diagram.
I.e., we have to
remember, if we go to
A, whether we
are in A now
and have been in C last, or whether we
are in A and have been in D last.
I.e., we will
create copies of A.
One for the
fact that we know:
We are now in A,
but previously we were in C.
And analogously
one for:
We are in A
and were previously in D.
That is, because of this history node
(in order to be able to return to
the appropriate place later), we must make copies
of the outer states and also of their transitions.
To be able to remember
what the last inner sub-state
was and
return to it.
To be able to use that
information when we have a re-entry
into that hierarchical
state via history.
That's our approach now,
a little more complex.
What does that mean
specifically in the example?
Again:
This is what
we're dealing with.
And first, in the simple
case, we want to keep
things outside (the
simple states) essentially.
That first leads to the fact
that we can start like this.
That we keep the basic states A,
B, C, D, X and already know that
we're not really going
to need that starting state.
We can
remove it later.
That was
an inner one.
And the outer
one we're going to
use to also have it as the
starting state for the whole flat state diagram.
That's what
we're seeing here.
We're also already
seeing, as a reminder:
In the simple case, we can
keep transitions that don't have anything
to do with entering or
exiting to/from a hierarchical state.
That's sort of the
part where we say:
Other transitions, which therefore do not have anything
to do with entries or exits, are kept.
That means in this concrete case that
we can keep these and these transitions
because they don't somehow touch
the edge of a hierarchical state.
Then we
are here.
The outer starting state, we can
also just take advantage of that.
And we don't need
this one in here.
It's only needed if we
have an entry into this
part via a standard entry,
which would be this one.
So because that was the
starting state of this inner complex,
and there was a standard entry
there from X, we get this transition.
This corresponds to the information: standard entry
under the start state, therefore this transition.
What else do
we have to translate?
We know that we always get
to A from here with e.
That's what
we see here.
There's a transition that no matter if we're
in C or D, we always get to A.
That would be
the easy one.
However, we know that we still have to
remember whether we came from C or from D.
I.e., it is not enough
just to have this transition here.
We also have to remember this extra information that will
let us know later (when we come back from B,
for example) that we are really supposed
to come back to D and not C.
So that's if we come here from D
with e and then come back with b.
Then we want to
end up at D.
However, if we did
that from C, which
would be possible, then we
want to come back to C.
That would be exactly
what this history accomplishes.
If we came from D with e and later came back
with b via history, we want to end up at D.
If we did that from C, we
also want to end up at C.
That is, it is not enough simply
to have this b and e transition.
We also have to somehow hold that
this is why we are returning to
D, because we had come to A from D. And there is just the
idea that if we do that from C, we will end up at C, too.
And there's just the idea that we do
that by capturing that in the states as well.
So it's not just A, it's
that A that we entered from D.
So in the outer states, in the A and
the B and strictly speaking also in the X,
we remember by
an extra annotation
from which sub-state of
the hierarchical state we came.
That's where more states come from, because we
have to do that for C as well.
We just
create copies.
What were in the UML state diagrams
A, B, for that we have two copies:
one for the fact that we came from C
and one for the fact that we came from D.
Strictly speaking, we could
also create three copies,
namely in case we could also end up
here without ever having been in C or D.
So one copy for: we
were last here in C.
One for: we were
last here in D.
One for: we haven't been
to this part at all.
That's what I did for the
X, created a copy here where
I don't write anything in the brackets
because that's supposed to be the information:
Here we are in X and we
have never been in this part at all.
In this specific
case, it happens that
we are never in X
if we have been here before.
That's why I didn't create copies of
X for C and D as well,
but only for
this simple case.
And analogously for A and B I created only
the copies for: we were in C and D respectively.
And not another copy for: we
have never been in this hierarchical state.
This cannot happen at
all in the concrete example.
That explains why we have these
two copies here of A and B,
but don't have
additional copies for X.
These are
the additional states.
And we also know that of
course we need the transitions in between.
So:
That we can switch between A
and B with a and f,
that is not changed by whether we
have been in D or in C before.
That also follows from the strategy here, that
we create these copies of the outer states (in
that case, of A and B) and their transitions;
these two a, f transitions, which we find both
here and here; and then for completion,
these states still have to be bound.
When do we
get to A(C)?
When we have been last in C
and then took this e-transition leading to A.
When we take this transition
and have been in C last.
That's why we
have this transition.
And we then use the information that
we've been in C when, again, we
want to go from B to D at some point
with b. So, if we take that transition at some point.
So if we take this
transition at some point, via history
nodes, and have last been in C, we also want
to return to C. And this happens through this additional transition.
And that is done
by this additional arrow.
That's where we use information, whether we
were last in C or in D, to
be able
to return there.
So that's the solution to
this example using this approach
or this essential idea in particular,
to remember in the outer states whether
or from which sub-state of
the hierarchical state you got there.
To then be able to exploit that when you
have a history entry like here in the example.